Why is there an arc of AI?
Hello and welcome back. There is an arc
of AI because we are using the opening
video which we shouldn't, but actually
thought it's generic. Yeah. And it's
not. Mhm. We shouldn't do that. But
anyway, not arc of AI.
>> I just found a bug. Yeah. Yeah, Marit
found a bug. And we're going to talk
about that.
Java Pro,
AI Native Dev at not arc of AI, but JCON
2026 live
Marit van Dijk. Yes. Thank you. My next
guest, developer advocate at JetBrains.
Yes. The producer of beloved by
everybody IDE,
IntelliJ IDEA, and bunch of other stuff
including Agenda ID, which is called
Air. Air. A
brand new
kind of
working sometimes, sometimes not, but
>> It's early days.
>> Actively actively being developed and
not general available yet. I'm not sure
whether it's like preview or or what the
current status is actually cuz I'm on a
different different department.
>> Yeah, no, but we're going to talk about
the department. We're going to talk
about the IntelliJ IDEA that is very
live production ready for the last 15
years or 25. IntelliJ turned 20 IntelliJ
IDEA turned 25 this year. 25 years.
Um and I have a question. Okay. Why do
we need it? I mean, AI does all the
code. We don't write code anymore. We
don't read any code code anymore. I
don't I don't I don't need to read code.
>> you sure we don't read code anymore? I
mean, from some of the applications out
there, I'm fairly certain the people who
write them don't actually read the code
or try using their applications, but
I think I saw a keynote recently where
they were saying actually do read the
code.
Um and I don't know about you, but I
prefer to read the code in my IDE where
I can easily navigate and search and use
other useful features like the debugger
to help me understand not just what's
going on when I'm trying to fix a bug to
to figure out what the actual bug is,
but also sometimes to
actually just figure out what the code
does from
you know, is my understanding from
reading the code what the code actually
does when I'm running it. So, I think
that's the point, right? I mean, what
especially now when code is AI
generated, it's actually even more
important
to understand to be able to easily
understand what it does because it's not
your code. In your own code, you have
idea
where to go and what to look, and with
AI generated, not so much. Exactly. It's
like code written by someone else,
but or an amalgamation of many people
that you don't even know and you
I sometimes you can ask like, why did
you choose to do this or that?
Uh but you know that it's also inclined
to tell you that you're absolutely
right. Maybe it doesn't know about that.
Yep. Even if you do ask, "Hey, why did
you do this instead of that?" It might
interpret that to be like, "Oh, did you
want me to do that instead?" And you're
still not getting a straight answer. At
least if you're reviewing your
teammates' code, then you can ask them,
"Hey, why did you choose this over
that?"
Uh you know, maybe they did think about
an alternative solution, but tried it
out and figured out that it was
suboptimal for whatever reason that you
can then
talk about with your teammate not in the
same way that you can with your AI
assistant or agent or whatever.
Um So, that would make it even more
important.
>> Yeah, I'm I'm still a very firm believer
that no matter how you got the code,
whether you, you know, copy-pasted it
from Stack Overflow, yes, I'm old, or
had an agent write it for you, if you
push that code once you commit that code
and especially if you push it to
production, it's your responsibility.
So, you better make sure that you
understand how it works and
Uh
>> And and obviously like a first-class
idea helps with that. Helps exactly with
with navigating the code and debugging
code and and and this kind of stuff.
>> Yeah, but I have I have a whole You
might as you might know, I did a whole
talk on reading code that I've done at
pretty much any Java conference and
other conference that would have me. I
will also be doing that talk at Devoxx
Poland later this year in June, I think.
Um so, you know, about how to practice
reading code and of course how your IDE
can help you. Yeah, and and it's again,
I mean, that's the that's the big deal,
right? Even if you we don't write code,
we we probably should read code that was
written for us.
Is there something different in terms of
how the IDE should work
um if our goal is now switch to AI
generated code versus human generated
code?
Well,
like I said, I think it's still our
responsibility to understand how the
code works.
Um so,
I would still navigate the project, run
the tests, look at the tests to see
whether they're actually doing what
they're supposed to. I have also found
many many creative ways for people to
have test files there that don't
actually run anything from, you know,
adding at ignored or at disabled to just
not having an at test annotation or the
most creative way I've heard is just
disable the Surefire plugin.
So,
you know, make sure that you run the
tests. Make sure that the tests actually
fail for whatever reason they're
supposed to fail. Otherwise, you still
don't know.
Um like I said, run the code through the
debugger to make sure that it does what
you think it does. Obviously, work on
your observability in production because
your users might use your code in ways
that you have not anticipated
um so that you can see what's going on
there. All of these things are are still
important no matter who wrote the actual
code. And speaking about you are not
able to ask your colleagues now, what
does it mean because there is no because
there is no colleague.
>> us. No, I mean, comparing to human
colleagues now, we have no colleagues.
>> Um it would be very useful if our IDEs
actually had the the features of asking
the agents about certain certain code.
So, if I can select like a method and
ask the agent to wrote it or maybe even
another agent. Yeah, so that these are
actually some of my favorite AI features
that we have inside IntelliJ IDEA. We
have our AI assistant, um which you can
use in the chat. So, obviously there you
can ask questions, which sometimes I do
like, you know, what would be the best
pattern or remind me how to do this or
whatever.
Uh but also we have AI features
integrated into the IDE. You know, the I
in IDE stands for integrated.
So, uh features like, you know, write
documentation or explain this code are
things that I use a lot. And also we
have an additional plugin, which is AI
experimental features that Anton demoed
in our last what's new video uh that has
an insights feature that will actually
generate insights on the fly as you're
reading the code with like a small
summary of what a method does or
whatever. Uh but not like if you write
Java doc, it can be quite verbose still,
Java, sorry.
Uh the insights are are really brief and
and short and
I find this very helpful as well.
>> Yeah. Yeah. No, I that's exactly that,
right? So, so you
even if the code is not written by you
and you're like, "Ah, I have like so
much code to review now." Yeah, AI can
actually help with that. Um which which
is nice. The the question is
can we trust those insights that are
that are generated?
Up to a point, yes, still. But you know,
do you trust the code? If you don't
trust the insights generated by AI, do
you trust the code generated by AI?
Um so, you know, use your own judgment
always.
Yeah. Yeah. And
it's also like multi-model, right? So,
you can ask questions about code that is
written by another model, which is also
kind of a safety net because they do
they do find problems with each other,
which is very useful. I I especially
also like asking it, "Okay, so it just
wrote me this code. Okay, can you find
some problems with your code?" Yes,
actually the following.
If you know, well, no, it doesn't know
anything, but you know.
Um
and in Air, I think we actually have
that. I I've only touched Air very very
briefly. I should try it out more.
Uh we have the option also to review the
code that was just written by an agent.
You can have multiple agents review each
other like, you know, your teammates,
but virtual teammates, I guess, but not
as cute as Tamagotchi. Not as [laughter]
cute. Not as cute.
Um but they tend to agree with you a
lot. You're absolutely right. Exactly.
[laughter]
Marit, thank you very much. It's been a
pleasure. You all stay tuned for more
episodes of
Java Pro and AI Native Dev interviews at
JCON 2026.
We are going to be back very very soon.
All right.
That was